we're live
welcome to meditating with john varvakey
we live stream
every weekday morning at 9 30 a.m with
mondays alternating between a new lesson
called dharma day
and a review of the whole ecology
practice uh called ipaya day we will of
course be changing the
pi date uh next time around
uh because we will do a pi day according
to the two streams the eastern tradition
and the western tradition
if you're joining us for the first time
you're most welcome for previous lessons
and said see the description in this
video
i recommend strongly you'd go back and
do the first lesson
and then do one or two lessons every
week while you continue to meet with us
and you will soon catch up and integrate
with us and i have an announcement
this is our 100th live stream meeting
so congratulations to all of us i think
that's the right way to put it
i want to thank uh everybody who is
contributing to this of course amara and
jason
and also mark and brett for helping
uh to make the such a hospitable place
and encourage people to
join the discord server community i'd
love to i want to i'd love to thank
uh the saying itself i love this sega um
i have received so much
uh nourishment from my involvement and
participation in it
um it is it is it's really wonderful in
both senses of the word
way to begin the day um so
thank you all so very much uh for this
and for your participation
and for your feedback and the way you
support each other um
this is truly um a great gift that we're
all giving
to each other so
in order to perhaps extend that gift and
give it to others can you please help me
by liking this stream to increase its
visibility on the youtube algorithm
at the end of every session there are q
a
please limit your questions at that time
to the ecology of practices
however you can ask questions from any
lesson of the course
for more general q a please join me
this friday august the 21st at 3 p.m
eastern time live stream on youtube
for our general uh q a i hope to see you
there
okay so monday was the new pioneer day
so there isn't any material to review
i hope that you guys are going over uh
uh
the wisdom of hypatia section on
epicureanism
you're starting to see which of these uh
general practices you're going to take
up
uh perhaps you're practicing uh the the
the desire cataloging practice or
and or the savoring practice generate
some questions for
uh for me so next monday will be a
dharma day
and as i've said the dharma day actually
sort of spreads out
on monday wednesday friday when we're
doing the wisdom of hypatia it's a
little bit more like a course
that means monday wednesdays and fridays
typically are longer
monday we will turn to talking about uh
the epicurean response to fear and we
will then build into
um epicurean encouragement especially
uh through philosophical companionship
and um
so uh that's what's uh coming uh
ahead i've been noting in
my life how this return
to epicureanism i mean when we when you
can return
and get something from it again that
deepens
that's the element of sacredness right
um and i've noticed in my life that this
return to epicureanism
and the remembering the sati
of anorexia of peace
through both the desire cataloging which
i done the maximization but all of that
is actually focused on
um the anorexia the pure joy of being
that we can practice uh bringing into a
touchstone awareness
through savory i've been noticing how
impactful that is on me how this ability
to return to peace starts to permeate
um as an undercurrent uh through my day
and so i've been very grateful for this
um i'd always tended to
of of the great of the four great
ancient traditions epicureanism
stoicism aristotelianism and
neoplatonism
i always tended to regard uh
epicureanism as
as sort of you know
the well-meaning but not that too bright
cousin
of that family um i thought there was
some value in it but i i saw much more
value in stoicism
and you know platonism um the reason i
don't mention aristotelianism
is that uh aristotelianism is taken up
into uh neoplatonism
so i've been deeply appreciative of
getting to teach you guys about this
i have discovered that there is this
reciprocal relationship
at least for my pedagogy that i learn
the best when i'm teaching others and i
teach
others the best when i'm sharing my
learning with them
and so once again i guess i've come
around in a circle
to thank the senior once again for
affording me this home
in which i can rediscover the sacredness
within
epicureanism so thank you very much
so today we'll have a regular
set we'll begin with chanting we'll go
into the silence it will come out of it
it is uh a wednesday which means
during the q a we will give priority to
questions from the western tradition
from the wisdom of hypatia
of course so
get yourself into position set your
phones up do not disturb
and we will begin when i say begin
begin
[Music]
one
um
[Music]
one
you get your silence set
so
slowly come out of your practice
trying as best you can to integrate what
you cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character communitas
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
i'll recite them aloud today perhaps is
a helpful
help precepts are a living thing they
tend to evolve for me and my
articulation of them
tends to evolve
in reverence and respect for the power
and promise of life i promise not to
harm
but to care for living things wisely
in the aspiration to enlightenment
in reverence and respect for the power
and promise of material things
i promise not to abuse them or misuse
them
treat them wisely
the aspiration to enlightenment
reverence and respect for the power and
promise of speech
promise not to speak foolishly but to
speak wisely
in the aspiration to enlightenment
and reverence and respect for the power
and promise of sexuality
i promise not to have sex mindlessly
but to love wisely the aspiration to
enlightenment
in reverence and respect for the power
and promise
of consciousness
i promise not to alter my consciousness
indulgently
to transform it wisely in the aspiration
to enlightenment
so reminder again that we have a new
question schedule monday wednesdays and
fridays people are concentrating on
questions giving priority to but not
totally exclusively
the questions from the western tradition
the wisdom of hypatia tradition
uh tuesdays and thursdays questions
derived from
the eastern tradition the buddhist and
daoist traditions
also a reminder many of you are doing
this and it's much appreciated
you're sharing observations questions
edifications
which are very very helpful
um and a final reminder because of the
nature of the wisdom of hypatia we will
tend to be going longer on monday
wednesdays and fridays
this question agency if you have dabbled
in other practice and feel so the so
feel see those things interfering can
you compartmentalize them with the word
like compartmentalizing to leave them
open
while focusing on the psychology yes yes
so you can just label them
right put them aside um precisely
because
they're interfering um and
that's going to be an important practice
so
i'm glad you brought that up because as
i mentioned i recommend you like so
you're cultivating your ecology of
practice here's a particular perennial
problem you want to address perhaps it's
you know an issue of self-deception or
perhaps
particular reciprocal narrowing okay so
what practice can i do that will afford
a reciprocal opening and what i'm going
to do is i'm going to try a variety of
practices
try them on and then select the one that
most
transfers to my life not just feels the
vest while i'm practicing it
that is an insufficient
guide the one that seems to transfer
transformative transference with the
ones that transfers most transformation
to my life
that's the practice i take up so i pick
a perennial problem
right i pick up practice and then i try
a variety and then i'm going to look for
the one that's transformative that might
not be the one that my mind
initially enjoys the most or likes the
most
right sometimes it is but sometimes it
isn't
and so when aiden's pointing out once we
do that selection we need to sometimes
we've been practicing these other ones
and we've built up a bit of habit around
them
and we need to put them aside we need to
put them aside and we need to be
sort of gently label them yes and
they're just putting them aside
and returning to the practice it's very
much like what you're doing
in the meditative practice so thank you
aiden for saying that
and for bringing that up i think that is
a very astute
and helpful thing especially there's a
kairos around it
at this time the timing of what you said
i think is very well placed
uh mark uh hey mark uh
observation tried some saving today but
i have a messy office and not a lot of
connections came up for me
because it's laid out much like my mind
all over the place yes
um very good observation that's why
um i i i i use the metaphor but i should
emphasize it
uh so uh mcclelland's metaphor that
epicureanism is about being in the
garden
and savoring should be sort of turning
something into a garden
now eventually that will be possible
sort of no matter
where you are uh but it's a very good
idea to do this practice for a very long
time
in a natural setting uh that's the
evolutionary
you know machinery there's the bio fight
philia hypothesis
uh that we and there's increasing
evidence that we're in when we're in
natural settings
we move to a more optimal functioning so
we want more
more natural living things around us so
i walk in an area obviously it's
it's um it's in an urban area i go
walking through a residential area where
people have their gardens and they have
their hedges and their lawns
and there's trees and so there's enough
there that the savoring works
so try as much as possible for a long
time
to have the savoring in situations
right uh where you can uh
experience like a garden uh that there's
biophilia
involved i strongly recommend that the
other thing you could do is to zero in
the savoring
on very specific things like eating some
food
uh do the savoring or drinking some
water during the savory but
i understand mark's point when you're
doing the more the walking practice the
more expansive practice the moving
practice
then uh yes uh be in a place
that is rich with the potential for
biophilia and therefore
uh is most likely uh to
trigger this primordial these practice
primordial processing
so that it can eventually be exacted up
into
uh the more technological um environment
we often find ourselves
uh in an in in a prevalent fashion
uh robert gray uh here's an object hey
hi robert i did answer you
robert uh emailed in response uh to your
pen pal questions
um uh robert says the best 36 minutes of
my day
didn't realize it was 36 minutes thank
you john jason omar thank you all
uh thank you robert and it brings it
warms my heart
brings joy to me to know that this is
helping you because you're a good person
and it is a good thing to help good
people become better
um really really hey it's a really good
thing
and think about that it is a good thing
to help
good people become better and think
about savoring that
think about savoring that and think
about philosophical companionship
his philosophical companionship is a
practice about you know
finding and relating to you know good
people making and helping them you're
not making them better
but helping them become better it is a
really good thing to help good people
become better
uh crownsource i don't think i've met
you before so welcome
um my experience during the practice
reminds me of worship in church
in my christian days intense atmosphere
of peace a kind of sacredness a
different kind of presence that commands
gentle reverence
um
thank you for sharing that
that is how
it should be that is how it should be
that is why what i aspire to because
that is the home
which will do exactly what i was just
talking about
so thank you for sharing that means a
lot to me thank you
karima cynthia clayton in analyzing
desires what is the role of resistance i
find i savor it more than i used to it
seems to herald
your growth that's cool that's cool so
you can actually
savor the i'm understanding you
correctly cream you can actually
savor the experience of resistance
itself because for you there's been an
aspect shift
it now presents itself not just as
resistance
but as a ground an opening an
opportunity for growth
that that is really good that's going to
go that goes towards what's called
the silver lining principle in edonic
editing
we're going to talk about this when we
talk about the four-fold cure of
epicureanism
um if you can this is if so
i'll go in more depth later but the
silver lining principle is
and people misunderstand it is it it's
not it's not just
finding the silver lining it's aspect
shifting
so that right the silver lining isn't
you know within this the negative dark
cloud
the silver lining is a access point
so that you can shift the entire aspect
of the thing you're looking at um and
you
so it's no longer sort of um
overshadowed hey that works right with
dark clouds
rather than being overshadowed and so
being able to savor it
as an opportunity for growth i would
point
out that if you're finding that um more
comprehensively
that's a real marker of growth on your
part karima
i think that is a sign of
a a change at the level of one's
character
and always always always it's not
ultimately about altered
states of consciousness it's about
altered traits of character
you can change your consciousness all
you want
but if it doesn't translate into the
transformation
of character you are just engaging in
what trungpa called
spiritual materialism you're doing
spiritual bypassing
is another way of talking about it uh
from uh the psychotherapeutic literature
um it's but if if those altered states
like what screamis are are bridging
into the transformation of character
then
you are really on the path
another question from agency
what are your thoughts on savoring and
reinstalling technology
and our soulless industrial environment
yes aidan uh so there's a practical
response which i already gave
i think i recommend starting for a very
long time and this
comes out in you know rave kelly's work
on doing parkour in the natural
environment and
the whole movement practices i've got
videos
uh with rafe and he has his own channel
um
and so i recommend very strongly that
you spend
a lot of time in biophilia
i just went camping again uh this
weekend
uh i haven't done it for a while and the
parks are finally open
and they've got all the social
distancing in place it's actually a
place i
used to go as a child so it was a a deep
sort of uh
almost homecoming and the people where i
with or i was
you know most of the beloved people in
my life
um and so uh but but again just being
there
and there were that sense of how readily
it affords
anorexia i recommend practicing that a
lot
and then gradually trying to bring it in
as you said made into the soulless
technological environment
i recommend if this takes some deeper
conceptual cognitive work
because because we're natural-born
cyborgs the technology isn't just out
there as a tool
it permeates on mostly unconsciously it
permeates our very sense of self
and our way of sizing up the world and
so
some of the work coming out of heidegger
uh on you know the question concerning
technology and
ways of the way in which uh technology
insinuates an insidious metaphysics
technology isn't evil that's not what
i'm talking about i'm talking about
the way in which it's culturally
situated and it it
it's sort of an insidious right it right
it insinuates
and insidious metaphysics and
existential modes
uh into our thinking and so learning a
bit more about that
and then as a preparation and then
once you've got sort of that revision of
your cultural cognitive grammar
try to bring the savoring out of the
more natural biophilic environments
into ones that are more technologically
encompassing
that would be my recommendation another
observation from mark welcome again i
was outside taking pictures of my flower
yesterday i was savoring the outside the
smells and sounds it worked quite well
yes even a short walk lovely thank you
for this practice
so that's again so the contrast that so
mark has
been very exemplary here the contrast
between doing it in his room
and doing it in a more natural
environment is bringing out the point
um and so that's why i've given the
recommendations
and like i said just simply shifting the
practice from nature
into the technological environment that
that will work
probably but you can really ramp it up
if you read some of the philosophical
work
that is reflecting on the way in which
technology
isn't just things around us
it gets insinuated a a world view
an existential mode gets insinuated into
the very fabric
um and texture of our being uh uh
of our of our self
so taco and soho observation i feel calm
that's good so
here's where the epicureanism and the
and the buddhist stuff
really uh can be helpful to us
remember if it's the calm of escapism
if it's the contentedness of a cabbage
then
that's not what's after here but if it's
anorexia if it's the joy of being
if it's the if it's the mindfulness
presence
if it's the participation in that the
of being itself that active uh
calm the calm that is the perpetual
affordance of insight then
that is the calm we're after matthew
mccready
observation i generally think in words
and lesson images but during this course
i definitely feel my imaginative skills
develop as i can imagine my inner world
etc
that is um that is widely reported that
meditative practices
open up the inner senses um that's why
they reported i also
noted that it's reported um that
people's experience becomes more
synesthetic um
synthetic becomes more symptomatic uh
more
there's more secret uh synchronicities
uh so all of these things
tend to increase the whole imaginal
realm
as opposed to the merely imaginary the
whole imaginal realm
uh opens up quite profoundly um
with the these extended practices this
ecology practice
uh so thank you for sharing that and
that is something to savor um
it really is it's a way of coming alive
that your inner life
comes alive as you start to get a felt
sense of what it is to move beyond um
the prop the the merely propositional
into the procedural and the perspective
that's what the imagery is doing and
then when it's transforming your
character
that's ultimately the participatory
so our last uh question uh
taquin soho i was wondering about
spiritual materialism would love to know
more about the subject so there's a book
written by trungpa
called spiritual materialism uh there's
also
i don't remember there's a book but
there's articles within
uh psycho psychotherapeutic uh
research called spiritual bypassing so
you can
pick up the book by trungpa called
spiritual materialism
sorry it's called cutting through
spiritual materialism um and then you
can
i recommend that that that's that's good
and it's it's considered a classic
uh uh but i also recommend taking a look
within the psychotherapeutic
community perhaps you know doing a
google scholar search or a google search
on
uh spiritual bypassing uh because um
there's there's an added nuance um
and education there that you won't find
in
cutting through spiritual materialism
all right
everybody uh thank you so much for
joining amara was with us here today so
i want to thank my dear friend
i know and techno major maher i want to
thank my beloved jason who's also
working behind the scenes please
subscribe to this channel to be notified
of the next video
also please follow me on twitter for any
updates about these streams
invite others who might benefit by
sharing this series
join the discord server to chat with
others do group lectio divina
uh do the group movement practice do
another sip for a longer time
um also i'm there for uh live q and a's
the people on voices with raviki with me
also meet there for a very valuable q as
and also uh the discord server is going
to hone uh
some of the group practices that we are
going to need
as we cultivate the wisdom of hypatia
reminded that we're doing this every
weekday morning at 9 30 eastern time
and please remember the continuity of
practice
is more important than sure quantity of
practice don't hold yourself to the
standard of
harsh perfectionism hold yourself to the
standard of virtuous friendship
because there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body but there's no
friend
no ally no true companion on the path
better than your own
mind and body be lamps unto yourselves
and to each other take good care
everyone i'll see you tomorrow